<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-08T17:36:19+00:00</updated><id>https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Microscopic Secret Tumors Tried to Keep</title><link href="https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/blog/2025/lactate-and-lactic-acid/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Microscopic Secret Tumors Tried to Keep"/><published>2025-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/blog/2025/lactate-and-lactic-acid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/blog/2025/lactate-and-lactic-acid/"><![CDATA[<p>For years, we’ve known that tumors are acidic. Most papers cite an average extracellular pH around 6.8, a bit lower than the normal 7.4. It’s been a foundational idea in cancer metabolism and drug development.</p> <p>But when we began working with Pegsitacianine, a nanoprobe that only activates below pH 5.3, something didn’t add up. In clinical trials, the signal was strong—too strong to be explained by a pH of 6.8. If tumors were really that acidic, why hadn’t we seen it earlier?</p> <p>So we took a closer look.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/fengqqhomepage/assets/img/post/SPEAR.png" alt="SPEAR nanoprobe imaging showing acidic regions in tumors" title="SPEAR nanoprobe imaging"/> </div> </div> <p>Using a series of ultra-pH-sensitive nanoprobes, each designed to switch on at different pH thresholds, we embedded tumor cells in a 3D gel and tracked where the acid went. What we found was not a gentle, uniform acidification, but a highly directional, focused release—almost like a jet—creating a sharply acidic zone right next to the cell.</p> <p>We called it SPEAR: Severely Polarized Extracellular Acidic Region.</p> <p>This wasn’t a fluke. Across different cancer types—lung, breast, head and neck—we saw the same pattern. Real patient samples showed it too. SPEARs form small, acidic “pockets” with pH &lt; 5.3, far more acidic than what any average measurement would show.</p> <p>And they weren’t just chemically interesting. These acidic spots were immune deserts. CD8+ T cells avoided them. In cell culture, we saw why—T cells died quickly in that level of acidity, while cancer cells didn’t seem to mind. SPEARs, it turns out, aren’t just acidic—they’re hostile to immune cells.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/fengqqhomepage/assets/img/post/Lactate2.png" alt="Lactate metabolism and T cell exclusion in acidic regions" title="Lactate and T cell interaction"/> </div> </div> <p>The mechanism pointed to monocarboxylate transporters (MCTs), which export lactic acid. Block MCTs, and the acidity beam disappears. It’s a simple idea: tumors build sharp acidity gradients to push back against the immune system.</p> <p>But here’s the twist. A couple of years ago, we published another study showing that lactate, the same molecule that’s exported alongside protons, can actually help T cells—if it’s separated from the acidity. In its neutral form, lactate supports T cell stemness and persistence in tumors.</p> <p>So we’re looking at two sides of the same molecule. When coupled with protons, it’s immune-suppressive. When decoupled, it’s immune-supportive. Same metabolite, opposite effects—depending on the microenvironment.</p> <p>In hindsight, it makes sense why average pH readings failed us. Tumors aren’t homogeneous; they’re patchy, asymmetric, and strategic. What we thought was a general “acidity” is actually a localized defense mechanism—a trench, not a fog.</p> <p>This project started with an unexpected clinical signal and ended with a very physical insight: tumors are more precise in their metabolic architecture than we thought. Now, with tools like UPS nanoprobes, we can see their tactics—and maybe turn them against the tumor.</p> <p>If we can target the SPEAR, we might be able to deliver therapies where they’re most needed—and where the tumor is most vulnerable.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research"/><category term="Metabolism"/><category term="Single-cell"/><category term="Immunotherapy"/><category term="Nanosensor"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How the discovery of SPEAR—Severely Polarized Extracellular Acidic Regions—changed our understanding of tumor acidity and immune evasion.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Remove the Barriers</title><link href="https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/blog/2025/remove-the-barriers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remove the Barriers"/><published>2025-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/blog/2025/remove-the-barriers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fengqq.github.io/fengqqhomepage/blog/2025/remove-the-barriers/"><![CDATA[<p>Biology is rapidly becoming a data-driven science. With the explosion of single-cell sequencing, spatial imaging, and high-throughput functional assays, modern biological research often begins not at the bench, but with a hard drive full of data. But alongside this transformation, a new set of barriers has emerged—ones that quietly shape who gets to participate in discovery.</p> <h2 id="barrier-1-tools-are-powerful-but-not-always-accessible">Barrier 1: Tools are powerful, but not always accessible.</h2> <p>Biologists often have sharp insights—creative hypotheses, unexpected connections, a sense of what might matter in a sea of noise. But turning those ideas into action increasingly requires coding skills. Even with the help of AI, which can generate scripts and automate workflows, many biologists find themselves stuck. The learning curve is steep, and the tools aren’t always transparent. On the other hand, data scientists may bring computational power but sometimes apply machine learning in a way that feels disconnected—turning rich biological questions into AI black boxes. When neither side can fully bridge the gap, important insights risk being lost in translation.</p> <h2 id="barrier-2-the-opportunity-to-do-research-is-still-limited">Barrier 2: The opportunity to do research is still limited.</h2> <p>Despite the growing importance of big data and AI in biology, access to research remains largely gated. Graduate students and postdocs are the primary engines of discovery in most labs. Meanwhile, high school and undergraduate students—with curiosity, time, and often surprising talent—are left waiting for a “right time” that may never come. The message is rarely explicit, but it’s there: the tools are too complex, the stakes too high. But if we really want innovation, we need to lower the barrier to entry. Talent doesn’t wait for a PhD.</p> <p>If biology is to benefit from its ongoing data revolution, we need to think beyond the data itself. That means building more intuitive tools, offering mentorship and early exposure, and designing systems that allow great ideas—regardless of where they come from—to be tested, refined, and shared. Discovery should be challenging, yes. But not exclusive.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/fengqqhomepage/assets/img/post/barrier.png" alt="Barriers in science education and research accessibility" title="Breaking down barriers in science"/> </div> </div> <h3 id="can-we-open-the-box-for-everyone">Can we open the box for everyone?</h3>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Thoughts"/><category term="Single-cell"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on making biological research more accessible to the next generation of scientists]]></summary></entry></feed>